Finding Aid for Smith-Parker-Hicks-Winegar Family Papers, 1821-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Smith-Parker-Hicks-Winegar Family Papers
1821-2012
1880-1952
Winegar family.
2012161 Aa 2
The Smith-Parker-Hicks-Winegar Family Papers document the history of several branches of the family who settled in Southern Michigan in the mid-1830s. The collection’s six series contain genealogical records, biographical materials, financial and business records, family correspondence, travel papers, and military papers.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated to the library in 2012 by Dr. George and Mrs. Lois Winegar (Donor No. 10354 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The collection is focused on the activities of family members from the early 19th century onwards. It was in the early and middle years of the 19th century that members of the Parker, Smith, Green, Hicks, and Winegar families moved to Michigan (mainly from New York) and purchased land. Among them were some of the earliest settlers in their respective townships. Members of the Parker, Smith, and Hicks families were farmers in Howell Township for several generations. Numerous family members were active in local business and civic affairs. The various branches of the family include a blacksmith (Archibald Green), farmers (Danford Parker, Emmett Parker, Robert R. Smith, Charles W. Hicks), florists (Nathan and Elmer Smith of Nathan Smith & Son), business owners (William, William S., and Frank B. Winegar, in lumbering and furniture manufacture), Civil War veterans (Danford Parker, William Winegar), a World War I veteran (W. J. Bryan Hicks), and three successive generations of teachers spanning from the 1860s to the 1960s (Mandana Hill Smith, Blanche Smith Parker, and Lois V. Parker Hicks). George Winegar and Lois Hicks Winegar, who collected genealogical and biographical records for many of the aforementioned family members, were 1952 graduates of Fowlerville High School.
The Smith-Parker-Hicks-Winegar Family Papers comprises the papers of various family members collected and maintained by Dr. George and Mrs. Lois Winegar. The collection is divided into six series: Genealogical Papers and Miscellaneous Family Records, the Robert R. Smith papers, the Blanche Smith Parker papers, the Lois V. Parker Hicks papers, the W. J. Bryan Hicks papers, and the George and Lois Winegar papers. The collection is thus organized around individual family members with the exception of the first series, which contains genealogical and personal papers of multiple people from various family branches.
Subjects:
Hicks family.; Hicks, Louis V.; Hicks, W. J. Bryan.; Parker family.; Parker, Blanche.; Smith family.; Smith, Robert R., 1847-; Winegar family.; Winegar, George O.; Fowlerville High School.; United States. Army. Cavalry, 17th.; Michigan State Fair.; Agriculture--Michigan.; Furniture industry and trade--Michigan.; World War I, 1914-1918.; Europe--Description and travel.; Fowlerville (Mich.)
Contributors:
Hicks, Louis V.; Hicks, W. J. Bryan.; Parker, Blanche.; Smith, Robert R.; Winegar, George O.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Genealogical Papers and Miscellaneous Family Records
  Genealogical Papers and Miscellaneous Family Records is primarily composed of genealogical records (including records dating to the first U.S. Census), biographical sketches, obituaries, personal papers, and financial records (including property records and records pertaining to family businesses). The first subseries (Early Genealogical Records) is predominantly comprised of the records of family members who lived in the 18th and 19th centuries, and includes records pertaining to their settlement in the Michigan Territory. The four subsequent subseries pertain to various family branches (Parker, Smith, Parker-Hicks, and Winegar). The Parker Family subseries contains genealogical and financial records and correspondence for members of the Parker family, including Danford Parker, a Civil War veteran. The Smith Family subseries contains genealogical, biographical, and financial records of Smith family members, including the teaching materials of Mandana Hill Smith, a strong supporter of women's suffrage and the first woman to register to vote in Howell Township. It also includes records for Nathan Smith, a prominent florist and the oldest continuous resident of the state of Michigan at the time of his death. The Parker-Hicks subseries contains the genealogical and biographical records of Lois V. Parker Hicks, a 1918 graduate of the University of Michigan, and her husband W. J. Bryan Hicks, a World War I veteran. The final subseries (Winegar Family) contains genealogical and biographical records, records pertaining to family businesses (including the Winegar Furniture Co.), and family correspondence.
  - Early Genealogical Records
    - A Table in the Wilderness (novel; fictional account of family members' settlement in Michigan in the early 19th century), 1959 (Box 1)
    - Howell Township tax notices and other financial records, 1840s-1870 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Parker, Green families, mixed genealogical records, undated (Box 1)
  - Parker Family Records
    - Danford Parker, biography and reference to Civil War service, 1892 undated (Box 1)
    - Danford Parker, account book (compiled in his capacity as county treasurer), 1881-1885 (Box 1)
    - Horace Parker (brother of Danford), Census records, obituary, 1852; 1870; 1880; 1900; 1903 (Box 1)
    - Horace Parker, financial papers, 1853-1882; undated (Box 1)
    - Horace Parker, correspondence, 1893-1900 (Box 1)
    - Elnora Parker Green (sister of Danford) and Archibald Green, genealogical records and property records, 1830s; 1842; 1880s undated (Box 1)
    - Helen Green Smith and Nathan Smith, genealogical records and obituaries, 1907; 1910, undated (Box 1)
  - Smith Family Records
    - Robert R. Smith, biography, undated (Box 1)
    - Hill family, deeds and mortgage, 1820s; 1840s-1860; 1870 (Box 1)
    - Mandana Hill Smith, biography, undated (Box 1)
    - Mandana Hill Smith, teaching materials, 1867-1871 (Box 1)
    - Ruby Hill Howe (sister of Mandana) and Nora Howe, trip to L.A. correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - Blanche Smith Parker, biography, undated (Box 1)
  - Parker-Hicks Family Records
    - Lois V. Parker Hicks, genealogical records, 2012 (Box 1)
    - Hicks family, biographical sketches, 1884 (Box 1)
    - W. J. Bryan Hicks, autobiographies, 1924; 1966 (Box 1)
  - Winegar Family Records
    - Winegar family, genealogical records, biographical sketches, obituaries, 1884-1965; undated (Box 1)
    - Winegar family businesses (including the Winegar Furniture Co.), 1880s; 1904; 1906 (Box 1)
    - Winegar family correspondence, 1862-1893 (Box 1)
- Robert R. Smith
  The Robert R. Smith series consists of two subseries: State and Local Fairs and Agricultural Records, and Financial Records. The first subseries contains programs, tickets, entry forms, and ephemera from various state and local fairs, including those of the Fowlerville Agricultural Society. It also contains livestock and farming records. The second subseries contains financial papers, ledgers, and farm account books, including those compiled over the course of the Smith-Parker business partnership.
  - State and Local Fairs and Agricultural Records
    - State Fairs, newspaper articles, ephemera, correspondence, 1858; 1880s-1890s; 1914; 1919 undated (Box 1)
    - State Fair programs, 1887-1894 (Box 1)
    - Fowlerville Agricultural Society Fair, programs, 1889; 1901; 1936; 1939 (Box 1)
    - Fowlerville Agricultural Society Fair, tickets, 1888-1919; 1972 (Box 1)
    - Fair entry forms for Shropshire Sheep, 1887 (Box 1)
    - Livestock and farming directories, records of sales and breeding, 1880s undated (Box 1)
    - Ribbon worn as Grand Marshal of a 4th of July parade, 1880s (Box 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Financial papers and correspondence, 1870s-1890s; 1907 (Box 1)
    - Account book, 1870s-1890s (Box 1)
    - Ledgers and farm account books, 1880s-1890s; 1906 (Box 1)
    - Smith and Parker (Robert R. Smith and Emmett Parker), ledgers and farm account books, 1912-1951 (Box 1)
    - Smith and Parker, bank loans, 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    - Lydia Thompson Sutton Smith (mother of Robert), account books, 1894-1895 (Box 1)
- Blanche Smith Parker
  The Blanche Smith Parker series comprises two subseries: Diaries, and Personal Papers and Correspondence. The diaries date from the late 19th and mid 20th centuries. The second subseries contains teaching records and family correspondence (including extensive correspondence with daughter Lois and travel correspondence from a 1930 trip to Western Canada).
  - Diaries
    - 1891, 1892 (Box 1)
    - 1946, 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948, 1950; 1951 (Box 2)
    - Diary of husband Emmett Parker, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence
    - Teaching materials, 1880s; 1893-1896 (Box 2)
    - Letters to daughter Lois, September 6-December 20, 1920; 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Parker family correspondence, 1898; 1921-1922 (Box 2)
    - Tour of Western Canada, travel correspondence, 1930 (Box 2)
- Lois V. Parker Hicks
  The Lois V. Parker Hicks series consists of three subseries: Personal Papers and Biographical Materials, European Tour, and Other Travel. The first subseries contains remembrances and autobiographical notes, teaching contracts, and newspaper articles pertaining to teaching and local Michigan schools. The second subseries contains materials from Parker Hicks' 1921 tour of Europe, including extensive travel correspondence, photographs, postcards, and ephemera. The third subseries contains correspondence, photographs, and postcards from Parker Hicks' 1926 trip to the Western U.S. with W. J. Bryan Hicks.
  - Personal Papers and Biographical Materials
    - Biographical notes and remembrances, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes, 1991 undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs and ephemera, 1905; 1916; 1919 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1922; 1986 (Box 2)
    - Teaching contracts, 1914; 1920; 1922; 1942; 1944; 1956; 1961 (Box 2)
    - News clippings pertaining to teaching and school events, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
  - European Tour
    - Travel correspondence (typescripts), June-August 1921 (Box 2)
    - Travel correspondence, March 29-November 6, 1921; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Passport, itineraries, record of travel correspondence, news articles, 1921 undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Paris, elsewhere in France, sea voyage) (includes one CD-ROM), 1921 (Box 2)
    - Paris postcards, 1921 (Box 2)
    - Other postcards (Montreal, France, Spain, England), 1921 (Box 2)
    - Passenger lists, 1921 (Box 3)
    - Tour brochures, 1923; 1924; 1927 (Box 3)
    - European travel ephemera, 1921 undated (Box 3)
  - Other Travel
    - Trip West
      - Correspondence, June 23-August 20, 1926; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Photographs (includes three CD-ROMs), 1926 (Box 3)
      - Postcards, 1926 (Box 3)
    - Trip to England summary, 1970s (Box 3)
- W. J. Bryan Hicks
  The W. J. Bryan Hicks series consists of three subseries: Personal Papers, World War I Service, and U.S. Cavalry History. The first subseries contains Hicks' high school commencement program and post-WWI military ephemera. The second subseries contains government documents and correspondence, photographs, ephemera, and extensive family correspondence, all pertaining to Hicks' service in the 17th Cavalry during the First World War. The third subseries contains articles and other research materials pertaining to the history of the U.S. Cavalry and materials from various cavalry museums.
  - Personal Papers
    - High School Commencement, 1916 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Military Tournament booklet, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Second Army Maneuvers booklet, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1900; 1919 undated (Box 3)
  - World War I Service
    - World War I service timeline, undated (Box 3)
    - Government documents and correspondence pertaining to war service, 1918-1919; 1929; 1930s-1950s (Box 3)
    - World War I 17th Cavalry photographs (camp life in Douglas, Arizona), 1918 undated (Box 3)
    - World War I ephemera (postcards, songs), 1918 undated (Box 3)
    - War correspondence
      - January 7-April 11, 1918 (Box 3)
      - April 18-August 6, 1918 (Box 3)
      - August 10-October 30, 1918 (Box 3)
      - November 6 1918-April 16, 1919 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Cavalry History
    - Articles pertaining to World War I and the Cavalry, 1991; 1994 (Box 3)
    - Excerpts from Twilight of the U.S. Cavalry, 1989 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Cavalry Museum ephemera, undated (Box 3)
    - John Slaughter Ranch Museum brochure, undated (Box 3)
    - Fort Huachuca Museum brochure, undated (Box 3)
- George and Lois Winegar
  The George and Lois Winegar series contains materials pertaining to the Fowlerville High School Class of 1952, of which the Winegars were graduates. These include yearbooks, scrapbooks, school newspapers, newsletters, and correspondence. The series also contains a scrapbook entitled "Fowlerville in 1952."
  - Fowlerville High School Class of, 1952
    - Scrapbook (50th reunion), 2002 (Box 3)
    - Yearbooks (25th reunion), 1977 (Box 3)
    - School Newspaper (The Shield), 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Rosters and newsletters, 1977; 1987-1992; 1998-2002 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1997; 2002; 2011-2012 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper articles pertaining to 1952 graduates and local residents, 2000, 2001, 2006 (Box 3)
    - Fowlerville in (scrapbook), 1952; undated (Box 3)